Richard A. Falk Papers
Richard A. Falk Papers
- Writings
  - Correspondence Concerning Future of the International Legal Order (Box 20)
  - Course Notes (Box 20)
  - Design for a Preferred World in the 1900's (Box 20)
  - Earlier Version of Chapters 1-6 (Box 20)
  - End of War Statements (Box 20)
  - Endangered Planet Lecture (Box 20)
  - Essays
    - "After the Cold War: Rules of the Game" / Richard Falk and Tom Farer, manuscript draft, manuscripts (Box 38)
    - "An American View of the Perugia Convention" Peace & Democracy News, Winter 1984-1985 (Box 36)
    - "Democracy Died at the Gulf", manuscript draft (Box 38)
    - "Framing the Postmodern Mindset", research material, ms draft (Box 38)
    - "The Gulf War and the Underside of Democracy: Some Reflections", manuscript draft (Box 36)
    - "Israeli-occupied Territories, International Law, and the Boundaries of Scholarly Discourse: A Reply to Michael Curtis", manuscript draft (Box 38)
    - "Letters from Prison, American Style: The Political Vision and Practice of Noam Chomsky", manuscript drafts (Box 36)
    - "Lybia's Remedies in 1990 for Unexploded Land Mines from World War II and in Relation to Colonial Rule", manuscript
    - "The Making of Global Citizenship: Learning from the Gulf Crisis", manuscript (Box 38)
    - "Nuclear Weapons and the Renewal of Democracy", manuscript draft (Box 36)
    - "Positive Prescriptions for the Near Future: a World Order Perspective" / Richard Falk and Albert G. Milbank, manuscript (Box 38)
    - "Reflections on the Gulf War Experience: Force and War in the United Nations System", manuscript (Box 38)
    - "The Role of the International Court of Justice" in International Relations - Understanding Global Issues / Peter G. Toma, Robert F. Gorman, editors, photocopy (Box 38)
    - "The Terrorist Foundations of Recent US Foreign Policy", drafts (Box 36)
    - "The Terrorist Foundations of Recent U.S. Foreign Policy" in Western State Terrorism, proof (Box 38)
    - "Theory, Realism, and World Security", draft (Box 36)
    - "Theory, Realism, and World Security", proof (Box 38)
    - "Vietnam and International Law: The Past Recalled and the Future Challenged", manuscript drafts (Box 36)
    - "World Order After the Cold War: Learning from the Gulf Crisis", manuscript (Box 38)
    - "World Order Prospects After the Cold War", manuscript (Box 38)
  - Evidence (Box 20)
  - Excerpts
    - US State Department Legal Memo (Box 20)
    - Quincy Wright (Box 20)
  - W. Friedmann (Box 20)
  - Galley Proofs, Nation (Box 20)
  - Galleys
    - American Journal of International Law (Box 20)
    - A New Paradigm for International Legal Studies: Prospects and Proposals (Box 20)
    - Book review (Box 20)
    - The Future of the International Legal Order (Vol. III), 2 folders (Box 20)
    - The Status of Law in International Society, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - History of International Law of Civil War (Box 21)
  - International Courts (Box 21)
  - International Effects: Population (Box 21)
  - International Law and Legal Positivism (Box 21)
  - International Law Seminar (Box 21)
  - Interviews (Box 21)
  - The Irrational (Box 21)
  - ISA: ICJ Namibia (Box 21)
  - Henry Kissinger manuscript (Box 21)
  - Law and Justice (Box 21)
  - Lectures
    - "The Antarctica Treaty System: Are There Viable Alternatives?", manuscript drafts (Box 36)
    - Conference on Impeachment (Box 21)
    - "The Logic and Spirit of Reassurance in Relation to the Biological Weapons Convention of 1972", manuscript draft (Box 36)
    - New Trends in International Law (Box 21)
    - Stevens Lectures (Box 21)
    - War Lecture (Box 21)
    - War or Peace: The State of the Globe (Box 21)
  - Legislative Intervention (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
  - New States Revision (Box 21)
  - Notes, 1958 (Box 21)
  - Notes, 1961 (Box 21)
  - Notes, miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 21)
  - Notes, Vietnam War and International Law (Box 21)
  - Oil and Power (Box 21)
  - Outline (Box 21)
  - Page proofs (oversize) (Oversize 2)
  - Permissions for Legal Order in a Violent World (Box 21)
  - Photocopies
    - Academy for the Advanced Study of World Community Values: A Proposal Comparative Protection of Human Rights, 1978 (Box 21)
    - Contribution to Commentary Symposium (Box 21)
    - Global Approach to National Policy, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Global Conception of National Policy (Box 21)
    - The Global Environment and International Law, 1974 (Box 21)
    - International Law Aspects of Prisoner Repatriation During Hostilities (Box 21)
    - The Knot With Four Folds, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 22)
    - New Directions for US Foreign Policy (Box 22)
    - Nuremberg: Past, Present, and Future (Box 22)
    - The Prisoner of War Issue: Whose Crime? (Box 22)
    - Redress Remarks (Box 22)
    - Renunciation of Nuclear Weapons Use (Box 22)
    - Responding to Severe Violations (Box 22)
    - The Role of Law in Future International Systems (Box 22)
    - The Role of Law in World Society, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Study of Future Worlds, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Toward A New World Order (Box 22)
    - Toward Equilibrium in the World Order System (Box 22)
    - What's Wrong With Henry Kissinger (Box 22)
    - What's Wrong With Henry Kissinger's Foreign Policy (Box 22)
    - World Order in the 1990's (Box 22)
    - World Order Models Project [WOMP], 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Poetry (Box 22)
  - Politics of Law in International Society (Box 22)
  - Published articles
    - [General], 1966-1974; 2 folders (Box 22)
    - [General], 1968-1975; 3 folders (Box 23)
    - The Knot With Four Folds (Box 23)
    - Law as a Contributor to the Maintenance of a Peaceful World (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
    - The Relations of Law to Culture, Power, and Justice (Box 23)
    - Relevance of Contending Systems of a Public Order (Box 23)
    - Towards a Warless World (Box 23)
    - The US and the Doctrine of Non-Intervention, 1959 (Box 23)
  - Regionalism (Box 23)
  - The Relevance of Political Context to International Law (Box 23)
  - Reviews of The Role of Domestic Courts (Box 23)
  - Revisions (Box 23)
  - Rough drafts
    - A Balance Sheet of Regional Integration (Box 23)
    - America Menaced: The Military-Industrial Complex (Box 23)
    - A Mosaic for an Endangered Planet (Box 23)
    - A New World Order for the 1990's, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - An Explanation of the Extraterritorial Extension of American Antitrust Regulation, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - The Authority of the United Nations to Control Non-Members (Box 23)
    - The Beirut Raid, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Bipolarity and the Future of World Society (Box 23)
    - The Cambodian Operation and International Law, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - Kenneth S. Carlston (Box 23)
    - Charybdis Responds: A Note on Treaty Interpretation (Box 23)
    - The Complexity of Sabbatino (Box 23)
    - Confrontation Diplomacy (Box 23)
    - The Continuing American Failure in Vietnam (Box 23)
    - Domestic Courts, International Law, and Foreign Acts of States, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - The Ecological Crisis of Our Age (Box 24)
    - The Exclusion of Nuclear Catastrophe (Box 24)
    - Extraterritorial Extension of American Anti-Trust Regulation (Box 24)
    - Wolfgang Friedmann (Box 24)
    - The Four Dimensions of Planetary Danger (Box 24)
    - The Future of Regionalism (Box 24)
    - The Future of the International Legal Order (Box 24)
    - Global Conception of National Policy, 6 folders (Box 24)
    - The Global Environment and International Law (Box 24)
    - Hazards of Freedom at the Global Level (Box 24)
    - Individual Responsibility under International Law (Box 24)
    - International Implications of a Technological Society (Box 24)
    - Introduction to International Law and Civil War (Box 24)
    - Morton A. Kaplan and Nicholas de B. Katzenbach (Box 24)
    - Korea Article (Box 24)
    - The Legitimacy of Zone II (Box 24)
    - Meeting the Challenges of the World Environment (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 15 folders (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous, 13 folders (Box 26)
    - Miscellaneous, 16 folders (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous, 20 folders (Box 28)
    - Miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 29)
    - New Approaches to the Study of International Law (Box 29)
    - Notes on Transition and World Order (Box 29)
    - The Nuremberg Defense in the Pentagon Papers Case (Box 29)
    - Observations on Political Loyalty (Box 29)
    - On the Quasi-Legislative Competence of the General Assembly (Box 29)
    - On Treaty Interpretation and the New Haven Approach, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Population Pressure: Malthus and Beyond (Box 29)
    - The Prospects for World Order: Models of the Future (Box 29)
    - The Province of Law in International Relations (Box 29)
    - Quest for World Order and the Vietnam War (Box 29)
    - The Question of War Crimes (Box 29)
    - The Recently Independent States: A Framework for Systematic Inquiry (Box 29)
    - Reforming World Order: Zones of Consciousness and Domains of Action (Box 29)
    - Regional Processes and World Order (Box 29)
    - The Renunciation of Nuclear Weapons (Box 29)
    - The Renunciation of Nuclear Weapons Use (Box 29)
    - The Role of Law in Future International Systems (Box 29)
    - The Role of Law in World Society, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - The Sabbatino Litigation and After (Box 29)
    - Sartre: Freedom and the Law (Box 29)
    - Settling Ocean Fishing Conflicts (Box 29)
    - Some New Approaches to the Study of International Law (Box 29)
    - Some Thoughts on Identifying and Solving the Problem of Compliance with International Law (Box 29)
    - The South West Africa Cases (Box 29)
    - The South West Africa Cases: An Appraisal (Box 29)
    - Struggle in the Middle East (Box 30)
    - Study of Future Worlds, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - This Endangered Planet, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Toward Equilibrium in the World Order System (Box 30)
    - The Trouble with Galileo's Victory (Box 30)
    - Unilateral Claims to Use of Outer Space (Box 30)
    - Unilateral Claims to Use Outer Space and the Development of World Legal Order (Box 30)
    - The United Nations: Notes on a Systemic Variation (Box 30)
    - United States Arms Policy: 1970-2000 (Box 30)
    - Vietnam and the Future of American Policy in Asia, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - War Crimes and Individual Responsibility (Box 30)
    - Why Impeachment (Box 30)
    - World Order Activism: First Steps (Box 30)
    - World Order Today: Patterns, Trends, Prospects (Box 30)
    - Zone II as a World Order Construct (Box 30)
  - Security in Disarmament (Box 30)
  - Southern Africa (Box 30)
  - Speeches
    - "The Americanization of the World and the Japanese Challenge", manuscript (Box 38)
    - Church Center Address (Box 30)
    - "Extremist Perspectives on the Gulf War", manuscript (Box 38)
    - "Global Problems and the Need for a New Global Order", manuscript (Box 38)
    - "Group Claims and the Nation-State within the United Nations System", research material, manuscript draft (Box 38)
    - Hearing Committee on Human Environment (Box 30)
    - "Religion and Politics: Verging on the Postmodern", research material, manuscript drafts, manuscript; other working titles include "The Renewed Relevance of Religion to International Relations" and "The Postmodern Challenge in the Setting of Public Policy" (Box 38)
    - United States and the United Nations (Box 30)
  - Stanley Foundation (Box 30)
  - Statement on Population Growth and Environmental Policy (Box 30)
  - Strategy of World Order (Box 30)
  - Student notes (Box 30)
  - Student papers, 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Typescripts
    - A Comment on the Question of Two Chinas (Box 30)
    - An Argument to Expand the Traditional Sources of International Law (Box 30)
    - A Plea for Systematic Procedures of Inquiry (Box 30)
    - Arms Control, Foreign Policy, and Global Reform (Box 30)
    - A Study of Future Worlds, 3 folders (Box 30)
    - A World Order Approach to National Policy (Box 31)
    - Basis of Moral and Legal Responsibility of Corporations (Box 31)
    - The Beirut Raid: A Case Study in the International Law of Retaliation (Box 31)
    - Bipolarity and the Future of World Society (Box 31)
    - The Cambodian Operation and International Law (Box 31)
    - Comparative Protection of Human Rights (Box 31)
    - Conflict of Laws (Box 31)
    - Confrontation Diplomacy (Box 31)
    - The Design of a New World Order System (Box 31)
    - Documents on Dispute Between Malaysia and Indonesia (Box 31)
    - Environmental Warfare and Ecocide (Box 31)
    - The Future of the International Legal Order I, 5 folders (Box 31)
    - Gaps and Biases in Contemporary Theories of International Law (Box 31)
    - The Global Environment and International Law, 1974 (Box 31)
    - Individual Responsibility in the Setting of Larger Scale Counterinsurgency Warfare (Box 31)
    - International Effects of Population Trends (Box 31)
    - International Law and the Conduct of the Vietnam War (Box 31)
    - International Law in Domestic Courts, 1965 (Box 31)
    - International Legal Order, 2 folders (Box 31)
    - The Interplay of Westphalia and Charter Conceptions of International Legal Order, 2 folders (Box 31)
    - The Knot with Four Folds: Unraveling the Future (Box 31)
    - Law, Lawyers, and the Conduct of American Foreign Relations (Box 31)
    - The Legal Status of the United States Involvement in the Vietnam War (Box 31)
    - The Legitimacy of Zone II as a Structure of Political Domination, 1969 (Box 32)
    - Meeting the Challenges of the World Environment, 2 folders (Box 32)
    - Miscellaneous, 16 folders (Box 32)
    - Neutralization in Southeast Asia, 1966 (Box 32)
    - New Approaches to the Study of International Law, 2 folders (Box 32)
    - The New States New Trends in International Law, 1969 (Box 32)
    - Notes on the Consequences of Revolutionary Activity for the Quality of International Order (Box 32)
    - Notes on Transition and World Order (Box 32)
    - Observations on Political Loyalty at a Time of World Crisis (Box 32)
    - Observer's Report on the Trial of the State vs. Eliaser Tuhadeleni and Others, 1968 (Box 32)
    - On Just Wars: The Case of World War II, 3 folders (Box 32)
    - On Regulating International Propaganda (Box 32)
    - Pandora's Halo (Box 32)
    - Pandora's Halo (Box 33)
    - The Prisoner of War Issue: Whose Crime? (Box 33)
    - The Quest for World Order and the Vietnam War (Box 33)
    - Realistic Horizons for International Adjudication (Box 33)
    - Redress Remarks (Box 33)
    - Reforming World Order: Zones of Consciousness and Domains of Action (Box 33)
    - Regional Politics and World Order (Box 33)
    - Relations of Law (Box 33)
    - Relevance of Political Context to the Nature and Functioning of International Law, 2 folders (Box 33)
    - The Revolution in Peace (Box 33)
    - Settlement of the War in Vietnam (Box 33)
    - Settling Ocean Fishing Conflicts (Box 33)
    - The Significance for World Legal Order of the 1961 Draft Program of the Soviet Communist Party (Box 33)
    - Significant General Assembly Resolutions Since 1966 on the Status of South West Africa (Box 33)
    - The Six Legal Dimensions of the Vietnam War, 10 folders (Box 33)
    - Some Thoughts on Identifying and Solving the Problem of Compliance with International Law (Box 33)
    - Some Thoughts on the Jurisprudence of Myers vs. McDougal (Box 33)
    - Son My: War Crimes and Individual Responsibility (Box 33)
    - The South West Africa Cases, 2 folders (Box 33)
    - The Status of Law (Box 33)
    - The Status of Law, 8 folders (Box 34)
    - Stress-Seeking and the Legal Order (Box 34)
    - Theoretical Foundations of Human Rights (Box 34)
    - This Endangered Planet, 8 folders (Box 34)
    - Toward A New World Order (Box 34)
    - Underlying Causes (Box 34)
    - The United Nations: Various Systems of Operation, 2 folders (Box 34)
    - Vietnam IV (Box 35)
    - The Vietnam War and International Law (Box 35)
    - War Crimes and Individual Responsibility (Box 35)
    - Why Impeachment (Box 35)
    - World Legal Order, 3 folders (Box 35)
    - World Order (Box 35)
    - World Order Today (Box 35)
    - World Order Today: Patterns, Trends, Prospects (Box 35)
  - Uncorrected Proof of This endangered planet (Box 35)
  - Violence and the International Order (Box 35)
  - WOMP VI [World Order Models Project] (Box 35)
  - Yale Ecology Chapter (Box 35)
- Memorabilia
  - Conference material (Box 36)
  - Conference material (Box 38)
  - Printed material, periodicals, miscellaneous (Box 36)
  - Printed material, miscellaneous (Box 38)
  - Publicity (Box 36)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 36)
Selected index to correspondence
This index covers the MAIN ACCESSION ONLY (boxes 1-35). Correspondents from later additions (boxes 36-38) is not included here.
Abzug, Bella 1971 1972
Bayh, Birch 1971
Brooke, Edward 1969
Bush, George 1971
Case, Clifford 1971
Cerf, Bennet 1971
Chomsky, Noam 1971
Church, Frank 1970
Eagleton, Thomas 1971 1972
Fulbright, J.W. 1971
Harris, Fred 1972
Hartke, Vance 1972
Hatfield, Mark 1971
Hughes, Harold
Humphrey, Hubert 1971
Kennedy, Edward 1970
Kissinger, Henry 1967
McGovern, George 1968
Muskie, Edmund 1971 1972
Spock, Benjamin 1971
Stennis, John 1971
Udall, Stewart 1971
Vanoeur, Sander
Weintraub, Joseph